A Guide to the Miscellaneous Virginia Letters 1827-1867
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Miscellaneous Virginia Letters 1827-1867
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
11176
There are 11 items.
There are eleven letters, 1827-1869, of various Virginia individuals and families concerning family matters, agriculture, politics, and historical events, including the Civil War.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This material was purchased by the Library from Timothy H. Bakken of Halvor Americana, Clarendon Hills, Illinois, on May 4, 1995; there are no restrictions.
Scope and Content Information
There are eleven letters, 1827-1869, of various Virginia individuals and families concerning family matters, agriculture, politics, and historical events, including the Civil War. Typed transcripts of the letters are included.
Contents List
- William B[ranch] Giles (1762-1830), Richmond, Virginia, to Charles Carroll of Carrollton (1737-1832), Baltimore, Maryland 1827 March 9, Letter.
  Concerning the gentlemen, Elliott, Lorman, and Patterson, recommended by Carroll and the fact that they "found no difficulty in executing the object of their visit to this place." [Possibly on Baltimore and Ohio Railroad business, as the road was chartered this year; Carrollton and Baltimore merchant William Patterson (1752-1835) were original members of its boad of directors.]
- William Slater, Loudoun County, Virginia, to Anthony Slater, [Zanesville, Ohio] 1828 June 5, Letter.
  Concerning family and friends, including the deaths of his brother Michael and Eve Smith's son John, and the well-being of the Slater and the Vinsel families. He discusses the hard times and the prices of wheat, corn, rye, and grain crops; his brother's estate and John Slater's children in his estate; and, mentions an affair of Philip Vinsel.
- George Slater, Loudoun County, Virginia, to Anthony Slater, Muskingum County, Ohio 1829 October 3, Letter.
  Concerning the estate and his lack of communication on the matter with either William Slater or himself.
- George Slater, Loudoun County, Virginia, to Anthony Slater, Muskingum County, Ohio 1834 April 2, Letter.
  Concerning family and friends, including the death of Eve Smith and the marriage of Mary Ann Smith to John Short. He discusses the hard times due to produce not selling for anything, and the prices of flour, wheat, and corn. He comments on national politics and Anthony Slater still being a"'whole hog' Jackson man."
- Samuel H. Slater, Hoysville, [Loudon County], Virginia, to William Slater, Adamsville, Muskingum County, Ohio 1855 September 10, Letter.
  Concerning Jacob's and his safe arrival home, discussing their trip through western Virginia. He discusses the Fourth of July celebration at Harper's Ferry which brought some fifteen hundred persons from Baltimore accompanied by the Independent Blues and the Independent Grays and the Brass Band of Baltimore. He comments on hard times and crops--wheat, corn, and grass, and on his affection for Ohio.
- Philip Vinsel, Hoysville, Loudoun County, Virginia, to William Anthony and Susannah Slater, c/o Harvey Cogsil, Carrollton, Ohio 1846 October 3, Letter.
  Notifying his sister of the death of their mother and discussing the specifics of her illness. He comments on family and friends; wheat, corn, and grain crops; and, the sale of the Case property and slaves in November. There is also a letter from Mary Cogsil to Susan Slater, concerning family matters.
- Solomon Vinsel, Loudoun County, Virginia, to Anthony and his wife [Susannah] Slater, Adamsville, Muskingum County, Ohio 1846 October 4, Letter.
  Informing his sister of the death of their mother, discussing the specifics of her illness and last days as well as the funeral.
- T. Stanley Beckwith, Petersburg, Virginia, to Charles S. Morgan, Richmond, Virginia 1847 September 6, Letter.
  Concerning the medical cases of two patients and the use of electromedical machinery in their treatments.
- Robert Hill, of the106th New York Infantry volunteers, Camp J[essey], near New Market, Virginia, to "Dear father" 1862 October 15, Letter.
  Writing of taking prisoners, one from Jackson's army, and relating the story of a specific prisoner and a visit from his mother. He comments on news from home including illness and thievery. [Note: the 106th New York (the "St. Lawrence County Regiment") was mustered into service in August 1862, and until June 1863 were on guard and provost duty in the defenses of the upper Potomac, during Stonewall Jackson's Shenandoah Valley campaign.]
- Jackson Martz, Rockingham County, Virginia, to Dorilas Martz (of Galva, Illinois) 1866 Aug 3, Letter.
  Writing a discourse on his feelings toward the war between the north and the south; the [Thaddeus] Stevens, [Charles] Sumner, [Henry] Wilson, and company school of politics; and, state's rights and state sovereignty. He mentions wheat and corn crops and prices of butter and eggs, and the problem of high costs.
- Jackson Martz, Rockingham County, Virginia, to Dorilas Martz (of Galva, Illinois) 1867 April 24, Letter.
  About family news; the prospect of wheat, corn, and grain crops; the prices of flour, bacon, and corn; and, hard times since the fall of 1864, with their barns and crops being destroyed.